well man I really appreciate you taking
the time to meet with me and this is I
think as I mentioned my email your work
has been just a spend medicine it's been
really healing and so lately have been
lately have been you know this last
month kind of really in preparation for
our chat no I read your book I've been
trying to following as many videos as I
can and yeah you put out so much stuff
recently it's just really been hard to
keep up with well there's a lot
happening and and there's a lot of
urgency and so you know doing as much as
I can really drank it it's amazing
so also the medication man that's been
amazing to you I feel like you know I've
been meditating or at least thinking I'm
meditating for the last I don't know 10
or 20 years but this has something about
the way you're describing it has I
actually feel like a meditating so good
really yeah so anyway I don't know where
you want to start I have you know this
could be an interview it could be just a
conversation what would you like
I think man I have a ton of stuff I'd
love to ask you but I think to keep it
with a theme you know our school we have
a training center that's okay this lives
on whatever referred to as the primal
hearts right kid basically looking at
you know all the essential skill sets
that we as humans have practiced and
preserved and continued using at some
level either you know from the
perspective that we focus on is like a
barrier you kind of fun
you know base look like you know
awareness and tracking you know these
are the skills of perception that people
have been doing since the beginning of
time you know and survival skill which
is you know the essence of existing and
being here skills with healing
preserving life and then let's go to
combat and so those four kind of
elements great like this this training
curriculum that is is the skill sets we
focused on and then we have behind that
a layer just to give you a little
orientation to conversation the the next
layer of scales is a focus on the art or
the experience of training and growth
and so there's kind of this a
multi-dimensional and multi-layered
training progression so it's it's kind
of a model beyond after the science art
and philosophy concept of or I'm sorry
the yes I'd be the true the beautiful
good that gave me kind of a frame of
reference so so that's then you know the
way I've set up is we have one class
every month and it goes around great for
a year-long curriculum and mostly it's
for local folks that live around here
but I do have some people come in and
I'm starting to guest up online anyway
the the where we're focusing right now
is a class I call know thyself and of
course following your work I knew that
was important and that it would be the
ultimate talk to you on that
so that happens to be and what we were
referred to as the tracking direction so
if you can you know I think of our
tracking courses have essentially real
layers of depth
it's the hard schedules of tracking and
then the the class we call the path
which is basically the path of training
you know if you will so it's and then we
get into know thyself with which is like
the philosophy so that's where we are
ready now just to give you a little
context and in this is yeah I can't be
good how big of a community is that you
know it's it it's been a dissipative
structure so we have people coming
dae-ho and it seems to be you know we
have we have kind of a base community
but it's also been you know something it
it seems what happens is it inspires
people they have that if they go through
our programs they kind of get inspired
and they kind of go through this cycle
and then end up getting released into
the world and doing that thing so we
ended up having a community an extended
community but it's not necessarily to
all here all the time you know so I have
I have a have a few students that
practice you know like martial arts we
do that
so I nice ways I mean it's I would say
its quality over quantity so we've
probably had you know that been here
through time like deeply probably 5200
people and then a lot of rip wasn't from
there how long have you been doing this
about 28 years
yeah the school itself about 15 years
and then kind of preparation for that so
yeah and are you say we who else is
working there with you um well actually
me my wife and then primarily I've been
I've been kind of the the head
instructor this whole time I've had a
few assistant instructors along the way
and but it's been kind of a small small
thing where I kind of act as a guide in
this experience of that basically it
there's a lot of I guess what
vehicles for it has been mentorship I
would say right right right
you it's that confrontation so wow
that's really cool
that's very well I like I like I like
getting into contact with these emergent
communities of practice in the emergent
ecology practices and I find it it's
really really stimulating and
thought-provoking so you found some
amazing ones yeah by tacwise so well
well one more thing I'd like to share
Thea's is from your impact is something
I found very powerful and when I say
healing you know I have a lot of
training in a number of areas that I
feel like be extremely powerful and one
of them has been with man named Tom
Brown jr. who's a tracker and he was
trained in the old way by a Apache elder
you know learned this very grounded and
very at the same time transformative in
even spiritual experience right so I've
been trying to learn I've been trying
I've been learning from him for the last
years yeah in that process you know the
the teaching style and the the culture
that it comes from is very I would say
their focus is on awareness you know and
the focus is on earth connection and
it's it's a it's a departure from our
normal from our Western perspective
they're a very I mean one way to explain
it is a very organized around space so
it's very how we're often open right
around time it seems they're kind of a
spatial right world and so a lot of the
language and a lot of the teaching kind
of
has to do with has to do with that but
there's a there's a reference to what's
called kayo teaching which is a a way of
conveying less uneven conveying it's
drawing people through experiences
instead of trying to give them
information and kind of we tend to it's
a experience gel pulling someone through
through mystery basically in ways that
they don't even know what's happening to
them and they end up putting together
their own experience and so very uh
what I've learned kind of through you
very Socratic and nature's globe they
use that yeah these the what's called
this sacred question or the art of
questioning and that's one of the main
vehicles so not because they're so
generative yeah they don't collapse on
the answer you know they expand into
yeah it's a amazing way to learn and to
teach
but what I found from your work is is
your precision with language and
defining terms and somehow building the
bridge from a very grounded scientific
you know place to to bridging all the
way to this metaphorical realm that I've
been learning from so the language is
often get to learn through is basically
a metaphor powerful and it works
surprisingly well actually but to have
this have it grounded in the physical in
this way or in how do you explain it but
it's been very powerful and very it's
filled in a lot of gaps for me what was
just the name of the teaching would you
say coyote teaching or what was it nimma
that's cool I don't know I'd like to
learn more about that and especially
that the art of sacred questions well
you could see why be very interested in
that do you written down or the videos
about this uh there's from this lineage
say there and this is a pretty broad
brought right group so when I said you
know 50-100 people that's that's the
people who were seriously with me I'm
their community there's a whole
underground movement going on that's
that's worldwide and so there is a lot
of material I only know of Tompkins
books Tom Brown he's written a lot of
books as well as but they're more our
story you know there's there is a
there's tons of teaching in them but you
can see how I don't that might be a good
place to start actually okay so maybe
yes please give me some links or yeah
that way yeah and then another reference
is John Young who's not a teacher of
mine he's he's taught courses in the art
of mentoring and it's been really
powerful so most of those please thank
you bet I would appreciate that yeah so
uh so yeah I just wanted to say the
value of somehow however you're using
language to spin at least from my mind
it's been really powerful really
effective so with that where'd like to
start is actually maybe just asking you
to define a few things even though
you've defined them before in your
material but I think for our audience it
would be really powerful and I'm also
trying to get people exposed to your
work so thank you so so with that well
actually you know what could you tell us
a little bit about your background in
relationship to this idea of know
thyself and maybe it'll kind of reveal
why oh okay well that's a little long
story where to start I came out of a
fundamentalist Christian background that
it's interesting no matter what how
people end up their religious upbringing
goes like it gets almost into your like
your into your DNA right into your
the the rudiments of your thinking and
being but I left that for Christianity
because it was ultimately very but it
was very traumatizing on me a lot of
ways and it became very antagonistic
towards Christianity religion in general
and in university I encountered the
figure of Socrates in a philosophy
course and it had a huge and profound
impact on me because I saw a way of
cultivating wisdom and virtue and what I
would later come to call you know kind
of spirituality I don't like that term
but that we don't have a better one
right now and that had a huge impact on
me and so Socrates is very much for me a
sacred figure in that I as you know
because there's all these thoughts are
like there isn't one Socrates I mean it
was a historical figure presumably but
you know there's somebody's has seen
through the eyes of Plato and then as
seen through the eyes of this the cynics
and the Stoics see through the eyes of
you know pero and skeptics or Epicurus
in the Epicurean so right there's right
there's this huge it's like a pebble
dumping upon there's issues ripple
effect that comes out and what what what
I saw is that I can return to that
rippling again and again and again and
when I do I see things that I hadn't
seen before and I challenged in ways I
hadn't been showers before and then I go
out into the world and that interaction
slowly percolates through my life and
permeates from my consciousness and
cognition and who I am and the way I am
in the world sort of changes right and
then after those changes I go back again
into that whole tradition and I see
things I hadn't seen before and then
they have for transformation
and transcendent and so this this has
just been happening through the whole of
my life the figure of Socrates is it's
it's inspirate he is inspirational
aspirational he write and he's
constantly encouraging me I don't I mean
that I want to really clear on that word
not just in the sense of motivational
but in the sense of exemplifying helping
me to become more courageous what
killing could call the courage to be so
Socrates is doing all of that but of
course he's also constantly challenging
any temptation and of course I'm very
prey to it you know to
self-righteousness or self-importance
and so he has been a constant companion
for me in a profound way and that has
carried into the project that he
fundamentally sees to be the project
that he sort of took although it's many
faceted the project he took is whose
central project and it goes by different
names it's you know he wants the
examined life because the unexamined
life is not worth living he wants to
know Tonica what's gonna meets me team
wants to know how to care and love
deeply and profoundly which should be
loved and cared about deeply and
profoundly he wants to know himself know
thyself and all of these things are are
constantly many different ways of
gesturing towards this core thing that's
right his love of wisdom and the fact
that there he doesn't give an answer to
that but does exactly what I said he
right he gives you these partial answers
that are always meant to take you to the
other answers and while while your whole
life is doing this right that's that
that's that's how he is has been an
instrument in an ongoing
I hope that answer your question yeah no
that's great um that sounds really
familiar that that experience sounds
like much of what I'm trying to scribe
with coyote Qing right I think the power
questions obviously so and then also I
just want people to understand that new
you're also a cognitive scientist you
are you know sure those those tell us a
little bit about work and how that might
really to notice though so yeah so I'm
not plugging psychologists are cognitive
scientists at the University of Toronto
I've been teaching and researching and
writing and publishing and you know all
that since 1994 and so I do a lot of
work around this notion that's
ultimately inspired by Socrates of what
is a meaningful life
what is the cultivation of wisdom and
surprisingly those questions we
cognitive science of the psychology have
gotten to a point where things that
people might not have originally
associated with Socrates or I can now be
put into deep discussion deep dialogue
with the Socratic corpus so as a
cognitive scientist I'm doing work on
you know you know the nature of brain
functioning or artificial intelligence
and yet it's surprising how getting a
deeper understanding of that actually
affords me a deeper understanding of the
Socratic project and so what's happened
is I've become very interested around
what kind of psycho technologies can
people internalized such that they can
better cultivate what Socrates was
trying to draw draw from them try to
induce from them and so and those are
you know those are you can see you can
see in
census of all of these in Socrates in
the dialogue obviously there's
mindfulness practices Socrates could
stand in place like in a meditative
state of 48 hours straight like just
profound abilities right so that's
obviously their stuff we don't know
about but it's only alluded to because
it was so presupposed the Greek culture
Socrates of course showed great courage
on the battlefield we know he he was he
had some martial art training
he's clearly spending a lot of time in
the gymnasium doing a lot of mind-body
work again they know just Plato means
broad shoulders because he was a
wrestler right all of this is just throw
presuppose that they don't even but you
know if you read the Republic Plato goes
a lot about how the body has to be
trained properly
so there's that there's Pharma teases
capacity for you know questioning people
leading them to aporia you know the a
realization of how much they're
deceiving themselves such that they're
they might be open to fundamentally
restructuring their thinking so a lot of
these practices are now practices and
processes that are being studied quite
deeply within cognitive psychology and
cognitive science so it's possible and
this is what cognitive science does
because because in kind of sites are
often trying to connect up artificial
intelligence how will you give these
abilities into machine you have to take
this weird question which is this
reverse engineering question so you know
given this process how can I reverse
engineer that so I can get it down to
its basic processes right and so I mean
and I mean this with the deepest was
respecting the rotom's we are getting
some of the signs that we'll have that
allow us to sort of reverse engineer
Socrates and what does that look like
and in connection with that I've been
you know these two ideas which is like
an ecology of practices and I alluded to
them already know Socrates is there's
some mindfulness stuff going on there's
mine you know there's mind-body
interaction integration going on there's
these quest
giving inside practices and then what
Socrates also exemplifies for me is that
above and beyond the ecology practices
and this was an idea provoked for I
Jordan Hall always be grateful for
invoking the right is there the sort of
a meta psycho technology that you know
collates and curates and right the
ecology of practices and there was in
the ancient world there was such a meta
second cycle technology that came right
out of the Socratic tradition and it has
the name dialectic the problem is if
people have heard that where before
they've probably heard it in Hegel's
voice and Hegel is much much later and
so he has his own particular post Conti
and slant on it which I think in some
ways is misleading so what I'm trying to
understand and what nc dialectic is is a
complex process and you have to sort of
walk you have to go through the Socratic
tradition like the photonic tradition
the stoic tradition of the Neoplatonic
tradition to try and get a sense of what
this is because it's both an individual
practice right and also a collective
practice and so a lot of my most recent
work has been trying to reverse engineer
that with the help of Christopher Massa
Pietro and guy sent stock in Jordan Hall
and Peter Lindbergh reverse engineer
that and do a lot of participatory
observation of very like these upon
taneous lee emerged discourse practices
like circling and empathy circling and
inside dialogue it goes on and on and on
right there right there's a week but
there's a reason why it's like this is a
plausibility argument there's a reason
why independent a second it's like
convergent evolution there's a reason
why independently all and now you've
introduced me to a new one right now all
these all these discourse authentic
relation right practices and communities
are emerging
that's a real phenomena that bespeaks
that's something there's a lack right
there's something missing right and and
so I'm trying to get in
that's I'm so pleased to talk to you
right now I'm doing all the talking I'm
sorry I'm just really emotional that's
great so right trying to understand why
are all right what's the lack what's
what's happening in all of these
communities like reverse engineer
Socrates and also do the participant
observation and try to get all of those
together to try and come up with what
dialectic might might look like Wow yeah
that's powerful you know something you
were recently I I watched the your
lecture in the meditation series on
lectio divina just as a as a practice
something you remind me of this I wanted
to make sure I I communicated that
there's something about that practice as
you described it was like oh my gosh
that is that's how we do tracking you
know that's we use you know rather than
the poetry we have all of nature you
know so you have you're actually making
contact I was doing it last night you're
actually making contact with some aspect
of nature and allowing it to you know
you're going through a similar process I
don't remember exactly you know I have
to kind of research how you laid it out
but it is this kind of ends up being
this kind of revealing conversation yeah
with entity and and becoming it and all
of these you know yeah there's all these
layers in that there's just like which
really kind of makes me curious about
how old that type of thinking is because
Tracking's obviously yeah yeah and so
you I mean they're tracking I mean
there's arguments right that that's the
one of the big drivers of the expansion
right lobes and probably also the
cerebellum frontal cortex
so yeah I think I would imagine that the
the practice you do is is harkening back
to something that's primordial Alexia
probably except Davina probably goes
back to antiquity within something like
the Neoplatonic period so made it
towards late antiquity and then it it's
hard to know and then it seems to
overlap and get taken up into
Christianity and a powerful work
I see Lex know as performing a very I
when I talk about it comedies and
practices and you look for sort of
design principles so you want you want
you want practices that have a
complementary relationship they they
have complementary sets of strengths and
weaknesses and therefore they can give
you a process of self correction within
the ecology and then you want you also
want layering it sounds like you've
mentioned a couple times where like I
have this practice and then I can layer
this another practice on it because this
practice zaps and makes use of the
preview it takes it up into itself right
and then there's linking practices and
the leading practice is sort of help you
progress between sort of them
the major nodes of your ecology so if
you have like sort of met mindfulness
practices here and then you have
something that is like has much more
propositional content in it but it's not
just propositional which is dialectic
then Alexio actually serves the bridge
bridge the bridge is between via logos
and mindfulness practices so in that
sense it's it's it would be interesting
to talk to you to see how because you
gave me sort of though you gave me sort
of forth towards a four or three I know
they would they correspond to true the
good and the beautiful oh yeah yeah so
for directions I actually use the
medicine wheel syuko technology as a
guide hello yeah that's been really
powerful and you just and not only
there's that's a whole nother thing I'd
love to talk to you
but the weight of that thing with
practice any of those types of tools and
I've kind of found a very I would say
the core principle based version of it
it seems to get your mind can kind of
map into it you know
so I actually couldn't after 20 years of
training of that kind of see the world
that way you know it's a small thing but
uh well yeah so we have four directions
which would be our four dimensions of
training and they have three layers at
the depth Beach so there's two right
right right so yeah probably trying to
be a holistic system right well that's
what I'm trying to get out within
ecology practices and I'm trying to and
I could be interested in understanding a
bit more
this isn't people mistake this were
because they take it to me and the same
as sort of making but when John Hall and
I talk for example about design
principles we're not talking about like
that you doesn't like we're talking
about the structural functional
organization that makes it work right
okay so I'd like to talk to you about
that at some point that'd be very
interesting yeah but so and this is the
thing like this has also been I just
want to notice them then a little trendy
fuck you it's been a very interesting
thing for me as I had gotten into this
and really try to study and enact and
embody this project philosophy other and
you know deal logos I found well that's
what's happening with us right now that
although the history and the content may
be different I'm capable of entering
into you know pretty deep discussions
with people from you know very you know
separate traditions and that also is
something that's really having an impact
on me it's like okay why is this what's
going on there's something deep is going
on here something right to me it kind of
suggests some sort of there's there's
some sort of core either realness or
trueness about that you know when you
yeah I mean when things start aligning
like that
yeah yeah well I'm gonna go back to my
questions just to keep to give this a
pathway but hello hello everything so
what how would you define so I'll just
make this very simple what does it mean
to know something and what does it mean
and we'll start with that what does it
mean to know something so I'm talking
about know thyself I'm kind of breaking
it down so I tend to I like that you
posed it to me as a verb rather than as
a noun you didn't ask me what is
knowledge you asked me what is it to
know which i think is a better way of
putting it
because if we think of it as an action
then we can talk more about doing it
well as opposed to trying to get final
features because I don't I don't think
there I don't think there's sort of a
final epistemological answer my
supervisor for my PhD described himself
as a meta skeptic meta skeptic is
convinced there's knowledge but he's not
clear there can be a unified final
epistemological account of knowledge so
that is sort of stayed with me but so
let's say it's let's think of it more as
something we do and then if you think
about the doings you can think about
virtues within there and what the
virtues are designed to do is to get us
into right relationship with the
normativity that is appropriate to the
action so I mean and this is an
Aristotelian point you judge how good
something is by getting at well what is
the normativity that actually regulates
its functioning so what well what's a
good knife
well what's it do what's a for cutting
right okay and what well then what are
the what's the structural functional
organization you need and what would
make it a good knife in virtue of which
notice the language in virtue of wit it
cuts well so I I start with the idea
that there's four kind
of knowing and then I try to get out
what's the normativity within within
each one and then what's the virtue of
propria to following that normativity
well if you'll allow me and I mean this
respectfully what's the virtue that
allows me to track the normativity
within that particular kind of knowing
okay so so I take one kind of knowing
which is predominant in our society and
I think it's oppressively dominant in
our society and in for historical
reasons I can't go into it's in the
series is propositional knowing and this
is knowing that something is the case
knowing that cats are mammals for
example right notice I have a
proposition all cats are mammals alright
then so I have certain Dan we want to
ask well what's the normativity here and
it's this very tortured notion of truth
and what is it for something to be true
and that's probably not quite work so if
I start going down that pathway I'm
going to slip into the kind of talk that
I'm trying to get away from so another
way of putting it is is well what's the
problem with the truth you know like in
propositional knowing well the idea is
well we fall into some kind of
self-deception about knowing our biases
and our prejudice make us draw the wrong
inferences draw the wrong conclusions
etc and so what we need are we need
practices that give us that the virtue
of good conviction that we are convinced
appropriately we are convinced well and
so I take it that uh so let me finish
this whole thing right please I take it
that the what we're talking about here
is a kind of rationality a kind of
inferential rationality that what people
have to learn is what's called active
open mindedness which is a way
looking for how particular biases can
affect and now form your inferential
practices your inferential activities or
inferential actions and so what does
that mean it means learning about how
adaptive machinery otherwise adaptive
machinery can interfere with my intern
inferential practices so let me give a
concrete example it's one it's an easy
one and that's what I like to use
confirmation bias right so but we're
making inferences we tend to only look
for inferences that will confirm our
already existing beliefs and we only
give attention to the evidence which
already confirms our belief so part of
what active open-mindedness is and it's
both is we're a little bit different
from standard vision right it's both an
individual practice and a joint practice
the individual practices they try to
sense sometimes myself to those biases I
try I try to look throughout the day
make a commitment it the bigger the
debate to look for a bias right but try
to look for a set of biases and
constantly reading about these biases
but you'd read a Bible just read about
them and read about them and read about
them and then when I notice a cop the
notice of confirmation bias and I do now
actively try to counteract it actively
reading and I encourage other people to
do that with me right give me feedback
on it so I think the propositional
knowing is to train your sense of
conviction which is your ability to
track the normativity of truth within
inferential knowing to train it with
active open mindedness and so now
there's procedural knowing there's
knowing how to do something and the
normativity there isn't truth its power
it's a sense of being empowered and so
similarly we need we need to be properly
trained so that we get that that
interactional fluency with things and
this why I'm so interested in the flow
state what are the conditions that are
confused
why is it so optimal how can it be right
how can it be misdirected helping it
actually and this is the right word
because the normativity here is in truth
its power how can it empower us so that
we have a more skillful interaction with
the world then there's respectable dog
this is the camp knowing what it's like
this is knowing what it's like to be
here now with this particular salience
landscape nope
so one way of thinking about it is
perspective knowing it's you know you
knowing through a state of mind into a
perspective and so it's how it's your
situational awareness it's your pattern
of noticing it's what you take to be
obvious right it's all of those things
and it's just happening for you right
now so what what's what what's the
virtue there well the virtue there is
presence it's about so you know like and
it's it's the virtue that they're trying
to get into into into video games
because what you want is the white
pattern of interaction so people right
are that but that has to be in order to
get the right pattern of interaction but
to give people a sense that they're
present in the world that you give them
the right sort of salience landscaping
and so you know well what how is the
self-deception there you know if you
know if you've got something like bias
for inferential learning and you have
sort of clumsiness or ineptness
or procedural what's the same thing for
respect to have a line well you know you
can it you can either lack presence or
you can project like you can be
egocentric for example many people know
what a limit when I mean when I say
that's a kind of error within
perspective of knowing because you're
incapable of taking the perspective of
another person so what we need is well
what and when you can think about what
I'm seeing here when you can't take the
perspective of another person they're
not really present to you and you are
not really present to them right and you
can be doing all kinds of this language
can be flowing but you know what it's
right you know what it's like when you
realize you can't I
wait we're just not in the same world
we're just not together right you lack
that co-presence so what's what's the
emergency there well it's very there's a
lot of mindfulness practices that are
designed to give us a you know a kind of
insight of the perspective a level and
so that so what I want are like
mindfulness practices in trying to kind
of virtue within respect rival knowing
so that I'm more reliably overcome two
tendencies for self-deception and afford
presence but my ability to do all that
my ability to generate a perspective is
actually based on my it depends on my
participatory knowing this is the way in
which my biology my culture and my
online cook cognition shaped me into an
agent and shape the environment into an
arena and it's happening below my
consciousness below my ego and it's
making all of that possible because what
it does is it opens up affordances for
me acutely this is graspable to me right
and you notice how the culture has
shaped this piece of the world and it
has taught me to shape myself to it so
that it's obvious to me that how I
should use this right and of course my
own mind my biology has done the same
thing
oh there's food right and right and so
all that participatory knowing is where
all this dynamical coupling and I want
to be really coupled well to the world
so and what's what what's the
normativity in there it's being in right
relationship it's being coupled in the
right way to the world so that
affordances reliably and systematically
open up for me
what's the self-deception there well
it's reciprocal narrowing where the way
I'm inhabiting my agency in the way I'm
inhabiting in the world they're getting
rigid and narrow and they're locking
each other down and that's what Mark
Lewis says is going on in addiction
what's the virtue the virtue is an agog
a where I'm open I learned right I've
learned how to in a reciprocal fashion
open up my agency and my arena so that I
get a deeper and deeper right
relationship to things that reciprocal
opening
so knowing there is to cultivate the
virtues that reliably afford reciprocal
openings so my sense of right
relationship and belonging is more and
more afforded and when I have a set of
virtues that link all of these four
kinds together that's the deepest and
can afford to deep transformation deep
understanding which is the really
grasped the significance to get thing to
be able to really track and be called by
all those normativity x' truths and
power
presents right relationship that's
knowledge but that's where knowledge has
finally become what I would call wisdom
Wow that was a beautiful yeah you know I
actually mapped some of those for and
ways of knowing and the virtues and
under the Medicine Wheel it's already to
becoming
I'm already embedding it into our
curriculum that's good
so if if like that I mean that's what
I've learned from cognitive science if I
can build a conceptual vocabulary and a
theoretical grammar that allows people
to take this as tools into their own
theorizing and their own like practices
and their own aspirations to
transformation and they find it reliably
helpful that that that's that's the most
important goal for me well that that is
happening sir that's working
that's really cool
so okay so that's what it means to know
something worry a definition how about
we tackle what is a self so that that's
that's the know thyself that he keeps
circling back to yeah so the thing for
me has been and this is very some
product right it's been not has been
trying to draw people out from
you know it get them to me get them to
move free from a way of thinking of the
self that I think is actually
detrimental to their flourishing and
this is a notion itself as well it's
it's a notion of self as a stump as a
self enclosed thing I sometimes call it
the the monolithic mind right that that
to have my self is to 2 is to possess a
point of self enclosure and what what
makes itself is it sort of its ability
to track its to talk to itself that
possess itself and grasp itself and I
think that is fundamentally mistaken
that sort of Cartesian view that you
have a self and it is sort of completely
self enclosed I'm gonna keep emphasizing
that there within your mind or brain and
so the the true nature of the self is
ultimate Lisa is something that is is
very subjective subject to you right
throw it underneath the subject and the
self is it is it is the normativity of
that is to try and remain very true to
that sort of fundamental possession and
this is very opposite all of that which
has become you know has become very
common language for us we think of
ourselves as inner we think we have a
true so and we have to be true to that
true self and I think this is very
problematic we can we can way of
promising it is to put it in contrast
with the Socratic notion and I would
recommend Christopher Moore's book on
Socratic self-knowledge the Socratic
self
is you it's not self-enclosed and it is
not something you possess and it is not
sort of already complete and you must
remain true to it instead the Socratic
self is something that you are aspiring
to the self is a way of talking
sometimes saying that there's not going
to be no self behind self-organization
what I mean by that the self isn't a
thing the self is a way of talking about
the way our cognition and lives are
appropriately important or right or
inappropriately self-organizing how is
your how is the life of your life going
right how is the self-organizing aspect
of your cognition right and your
cognition is dynamically developmental
your unit you develop as you're
functioning and you function as you
develop because your cognition is
inherently self-organizing so what
you're doing in self-knowledge is you're
not I mean you can you biography may be
relevant data but you're not primarily
celebrating or looking at your biography
to get your sense of itself you're
trying to figure out here's a
self-organizing system what I need to
know are what are the principles by
which they like they constrain it to be
self-organizing and how can my cognition
a here's another paradox or whose don't
lose the eye but how is this how is
right this reflective consciousness a
and cognition able to become aware of
the constraints on the self-organizing
so that the self-organizing occurs
better and better so it gets better at
overcoming self-deception better at
zeroing in on the relevant information
ignoring the irrelevant information
better at cultivating while all the
knowledge is we need all the knowings
that we talk about all the knowings that
we talked about right
so the Socratic cell
is basically what how have you come to
learn how like how do you let's put it
this way but somebody's is doing is he's
he's getting you to steam where do I
commit my resources my precious of
limited cognitive resources the my
precious and limited relationships to
myself each other where am I actually
committing them compared compared to
what I say let's say I am because your
introspection is actually sure right so
people think well I sort of I'd be quite
a look into myself no this is about good
it's not that effective right well I
state what I'm most most believe he
believes don't really capture this very
readily
so the Socratic project was actually
trying to get people trying to get
people to come to a poor head try to get
them to say well they realized oh oh
this is what I'm committing to and this
is on committing to it and then say is
this actually constraining the way in
which I am a fundamental way in which
emma is self-organizing dynamical system
in a way that's gonna lead it more and
more towards wisdom so this is this tell
is right the self is the way in which I
would argue your your your your set of
virtue of your character your your
habits of your deep habits of mine and
the virtues of mine they're to cognition
and consciousness your your your
dispositional elements your personality
and all of this is not in you it's all
relational it's how like it's a mind and
body are related it's how mind and body
and world are related on my body and
your mind and body in your world and
mine by up my mind and body my world are
all of that and how it well.some
organizes such that this particular like
mind body
like flourishes that's the self Wow
it's a know knowing that so if you'll
allow me a metaphor knowing thyself is
not knowing your story or of
autobiography that information is useful
but like you your story has actually
helped you to become a story is being a
story because that's what you are in
some ways you know there's no a story
you are a story being the story is a way
of trying to create what what I call a
virtual engine a set of constraints so
that your particulars self-organization
happens in a particular way that's good
but I'm asking people Socrates is asking
people don't look at your autobiography
or maybe maybe to be more more
charitable don't get fixated on just
your autobiography look at your
operating manual a lot more look like
look at your operating manual a lot more
try to understand the principles and
patterns of its self-organization
because the way you transform yourself
and also the way you know yourself
because they're bound up together is how
that self transfer how that self
organization is transformed when you
transform the patterns of
self-organization that's how you
fundamentally changing the self that's
that's really cool that actually ties
into something I forgot to mention which
is kind of the whole focus of this
little series in the mid king which is
the primal perspective and that you
naturally went there of course that's
something that drew me to you to your
work but yeah it's looking at the the
principles the processes as the thing
that's really cool would you say then
the are I mean maybe I'm getting into
consciousness now and that's might be
too big of a question but would you say
that the it's what we might experience a
self then is kind of an emergent
property of those two processes yes
totally and what's interesting is so
that knows
that we are sort of like like a soul in
the H in sort of the ancient like
whatever like the the ghost inside the
machine as I think as Rob put it because
I think there's a there's an older or
and also a newer sense of soul that we
could properly could rehabilitate which
is also to be able to live within it
again habitats right but yeah I you
think that that that's correct
because when you ask people how much
have you changed in the last ten years
they'll say oh I've changed so much so
much you know how much do you think
you'll change in the next ten years
oh I don't change very much at all and
then you ask him again in ten years how
much have you changed
oh I changed so much I've changed so
much really how much he gonna change in
the next thing is oh I'm not gonna
change very much this is the end of
history by us right so from right we we
think of ourselves as we we are always
suffering as if we're somehow we've and
this is why I don't like the ideas of
perfection that we've sum up because
perfect you you know to come into
completeness right to be finished so
yeah I I think that you are looking for
continuity of content in your
relationships so a continuity of contact
that continues to give you right
relationship that gives you presents
situational awareness they can't afford
you to you know acquire and apply the
right skills that then gets translated
into sets of you know sensibilities and
skills for how you move around your
concepts and you get that's where you
get the propositional knowing so
yourself you should be because you are I
mean come on you what what exists
between you and how you were as a
two-year-old is not any kind of identity
it's it's a continuity so right that
there's been this process of self or
zatia self-transcending developmental
self-organization that got here so
yourself yourself is in that sense
constantly changing it's constantly in a
process of dynamic change but of course
it's happening at multiple time scales
like some of the chamber so some of the
changes like momentary and some of it is
like it's at all different levels some
of its more you know this is like have
you ever had that experience where you
look back over the last five years and
you go 200 genes I didn't realize I was
changing for those five years at this
level that I didn't even know what's
going on at that time
yeah yeah I feel like I'm actually going
through one of those now and I think you
actually helped count something you said
earlier to I've got a check at the time
I think how how are you doing
the something you said about everything
being in the relational or birth or I
guess that's the perspective of seeing
things as relational I've had a real
powerful shift lately of I mean been
studying a lot of complexity theory and
that as well on that that'll do a number
on your on your but really starting to
tie that back into my training with you
know the lineage of track and all that
and how they perceive the world you know
any here all these kind of cliche like
everything's connected everything is one
almost kind of metaphors but but there's
actually possibly like it feels like
it's getting more more real to me like
I'm just like I actually see the world
you know like I say the relationships
and has things you know right so you're
moving from that see you're moving from
propositions that you might even be have
been convinced were true right into you
well and you're starting to get some
skills but those skills are actually
based on like you said I see the world
in a particular way and it actually
means that you write you know the way
right like the way you and the world fit
together at that participant
you're getting it you're getting like
your it's contra being an idea like it
it's percolated through all the or for
you right and so now right yeah it's
more real to you because you don't just
have the conviction of its truth you
have the power of your skills you have
the presence of the perspective and you
have the sense of being in right
relationship with reality and man does
that ever makes things seem real yeah
yeah yeah it's it's been pretty awesome
this is so fun Thank You Co one more
before yeah I had to tell you this I
just had a little Epiphany this might be
another thing but in your emphasis on
dhamma site recently or no how recent
that is but in your book you talk about
it and how it occurred to me that you
know for example I teach a survival
class is just a one day introduction to
do the survival skills and my kind of
tagline for the class is it's like going
home and to me what happened to me and
my development through these primitive
skills is it's it is a it's a homecoming
you know you actually go you go you you
you enter this this world where you are
directly connected to everything around
you in nature you know in a way that
it's it's not just something you visit
or something you go do you or you know
it's it's actually home virtually the
skills themselves there's this like
reassurance and kind of like this this
relief that washes over you when you
realize that you can with your own hands
and your own body mind you can go create
what you need to sustain life you know
out of whatever's around you in any
environment you know it might be a
bullet depending on your skill level but
you know it's like the potential is
there and it's so the access I just saw
that kind of as a heat one of the
healing
potentials maybe of those kinds of
skills in that nama side issue I think
that's deeply right I mean you might
have seen some conversations that are
with my friend Dave Kelly he's teaching
people you know the parkour in nature
and then the martial arts and the
mindfulness and then the the you know
the narrative practices and he's weaving
together this beautiful ecology
practices you two would get along very
well actually you do know him a little
good I met him this way yeah so yeah I
think that you know because he talks in
the same way he talks about a profound
kind of homecoming when people can be
rich resituated back into the
environment in which they evolved in
such that all of four of those things
have to click into place all the four
kinds of knowing yeah
and so I'm really interested in the
possibilities that we might have at a
more systemic level this Jordan Hall was
talking about this possibility that he
talked about the idea that up until
recently the only way we could get the
synergistic effects of distributed
cognition Minds working together was to
have them physically close to each other
and then the problem with that is what
is that we suffer all the dilatory
effects of cities or cut off from nature
or cut off from each other we get
Ottomans there's it really affords
pandemics it's mental really bad on your
mental health etc and you know this
better than I do and then he's saying
but we have the potential now where we
could actually separate those two
because if we could improve this medium
and improve the psycho tech and the
culture around it we could have the
distributed Minds working together
synergistically but people can go back
to living in you know small-scale
communities situated in right in the
environment in a you know
psychologically and socially and
ecologically sustainable and healthy way
and so that's a that's a really exciting
idea that I think we should be exploring
them because again I mean
so many people and I mean this is a
compliment to you who have we have read
what I call reinvent EO and the word
inventio means to both discover an event
so you have to eat exactly reinvent your
embodiment and embeddedness like with
what you're doing and how deeply deeply
healing this is and you can't tell
people from the outside what that
healing is going to be like now it's
it's it's almost like I can't tell you
what it's like to live in Spain if you
go and live in Spain right I can tell
there's a personal experience I can't
even I couldn't even predict it actually
because yeah we're all different you're
you know that's one of the pleasures of
being able to train with people and to
to facilitate and guide I kind of said
he teach but it's more of a guidance I
get it set up conditions and
environments in which people have
interactions with the earth and with
themselves and with each other that you
know these lessons form and they they
get things that I never would have
gotten so I get to learn the most you
know now we circled around the Socrates
again when you afford people right that
right when you afford people like
Socrates described himself as a midwife
when you had four people giving birth to
themselves in a way that they cannot
foresee because it requires you know
there are truths and I mean you know all
all senses of knowing like there are
truths that are only realized after self
transcendence and only through
transformation yeah I think that's
exactly right I think that's really
literally the case that you you giving
birth to other people is you it's it's
it's weird because when you're sharing
that with other people when you're
sharing your deep learning with other
people that's actually the best teaching
but it's paradoxically it you know it
rebounds on you and you do some of your
own unexpectedly most deep learning but
that's
next to that that's part of the
dialectic again right bringing that into
human interaction yeah Wow it's
beautiful well just maybe sneak in one
more thought one more question would you
say back to the self concept this idea
of the self could it since it is kind of
an emergent process couldn't be the
identity of self expand to include other
I mean oh it does I mean right I mean I
think your sense of self I mean and so
your sense of self moves or I mean we
know this from I mean not only from
historical records but also we're now
doing experimental work when people have
mystical experiences and higher states
of consciousness their sense of self
moves around like in really profound and
transformative ways and this isn't just
sort of epi phenomenal then again the
way they are self-organizing changes the
you know the virtual engine of their
dynamical system they are is it's
fundamentally been re-engineered in ways
that they don't fully understand until
it starts to unfold itself through time
so yeah your sense of self is
dramatically changed I mean one of the
things that right now in in my own in my
own practice I get moments and again
it's like wait we're talked about
earlier you don't you put them into
words and they won't sound deep enough
for resonance enough that the person has
to be in that world right thoughts wrong
there I get moments where so so you know
most most prominent you know egocentric
everything is self referential you know
I'm self importantly import to take in
self important of all that stuff and
then you get moments I have moments
where I'm aunt eccentric I'm actually
centered right on our realness I'm
centered on that realization being real
the way you talked about it which is
not the same thing as the inflation of
the ego and you get you get moments
where you taste the release from that
sort of you know that that fever longer
framing that we're in all the time and
we don't even realize it
but we get release from it in moments of
flow or in these kinds of experiences
and you get a sense of a way of being a
self that's not and this sounds like a
contradiction and that's probably very
telling a way of being yourself that's
not fundamentally egocentric but Anto
centric and I get us you get that sense
of you know Nirvana means to blow out
you know the flame you get a sense of
like it's like you get a wave of relief
and release that passes through your
entire being oh I think I get a sense of
but what how it could be and that's very
encouraging again it's very aspirational
II motivated so yeah I think no you
don't want to just dump that into people
like you don't just take a novice and
drop them into that because like yoga
you freak them out right I mean you
shouldn't do that that's immoral but on
the other hand you know you you got a
drop you've got to drop the breadcrumbs
that might lead people there and you got
to look for the breadcrumbs that other
people have left you so that you can
keep moving towards them that's one of
the beauties of working I guess close to
the earth or with nature nature so
honest you can't really skip steps you
know yeah requires grounded literally
right so yeah the yeah so it seems like
being the self the self idea that we're
talking about just this emergent thing
it kind of depends on where you want to
place this imaginary bound to be or
distinction in a sense of what do you
want to include it or what do you need
to include in that moment and that's
yeah I think that's boundaries around
well I mean we didn't get to talk about
it but I but this sort of deep process
of relevance realization what's inside
my
frame what's outside my how it moves
around and you know and there's
mysterious aspects to me I can't ever
bring the framing process itself fully
into bite my frame and you know my
framing of the world as you said is
constantly being challenged by the world
and opened up yeah and so when we go
through altered states of consciousness
that lead to alter traits of character
the fundamental ways in which were
framing the world but we find relevant
and salient what we Center on on the
egocentric the aunt eccentric for
example that shift around and I think
that if what I said is true if the felt
if the self is fundamentally the way
we're in a coupled fashion
self-organizing then that's that's what
it is for the self to be changed that
that process of relevance realization
and framing like has been fundamentally
fundamental framing has been
fundamentally transformed and so that's
well it is for the sense of self to be
altered that's perfect I think that's
that's a beautiful place to stop right
there they that's some will chew on
thank you yeah so again I just really
appreciate your time and take me a rest
to see what we're up to and maybe we can
continue that but regardless I do just
just appreciate your work and I really
want to get it out there so is it is
there anything you want to include in
terms of what you're up to that I know
obviously there's the awakening from the
meaning crisis series which has been I
think it's as huge education and
anything else you wanna mention well I
mean I'm hoping you'll also send me the
files for this conversation so I can
upload it I mean I'll give you priority
you upload it to your channel first and
then yeah okay well I mean I also I'm
doing and this when I mentioned that is
I want to put this on voices with
reveille key where I'm trying to
exemplify and also cultivate and talk
you know dialectic and deilogos doing
this and so that that's happening I'm
working on the next big historical
cognitive scientific video series called
after Socrates around what basically
what a lot of what we were talking about
today and that series will also not just
be like awakening from the meeting
crisis where it's mostly sort of theory
they'll also be you know exemplification
practice elements in it as well because
what I want to do is like I said I want
to try and you know reverse engineer
Socratic dialectic and put it into deep
dialogue with all like yourself all
these beat all these people and all
these practices are you know authentic
relating and you know sacred questioning
as you put it I think that's a beautiful
phrase by the way I love that so that
and that's a big project right now that
I'm working on a lot with Greg on leaks
I'll be we are going to be releasing a
series of videos that will present sort
of my overall argument about
consciousness and he will be interacting
with me in in a Socratic fashion because
he has his medicine ecology project
that's going to be called on tangling
the world nod of consciousness the hard
problems of mind and meaning and so
that's going to come out that's going to
come out soon
we've already filmed the first episode
we're going to be doing a sequence of
those and then people should know about
and you mentioned it already every
weekday morning I do the meditation and
contemplation online course and there's
a wonderful Sangha there that practices
and I mean I highly recommend it oh
thank you
and then now associated with that if
your people are interested there's a
discord server
over a thousand people along there now
it's growing community talking about
awakening from the meeting crisis voices
with vervain key the meditation class
right all of them so yeah
awesome right on well well thank you sir
and we shall look forward to maybe
hearing more from you in the future and
you're asking of my intent I'm very
happy to meet with you and talk again I
would like I would love to do that
sounds great right will you take care
and good luck in your work thank you so
much been really much really appreciate
it a very good time
I always say that it's been good
dialectic a few people can get to a
place together that they couldn't get to
on their own and I would I was hearing
in some of my answers to you and how
they were provoked by you and I mean
provoked in a good way I was hearing
things I hadn't said before I was making
connections that I hadn't made before so
that was very helpful to me thank you
very much Mike Weiss thank you take care
keep coming okay ANCA